<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!--
 Copyright (c) 1993 - 2007 Tim Riker

 This package is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 it under the terms of the license found in the file named COPYING
 that should have accompanied this file.

 THIS PACKAGE IS PROVIDED ``AS IS'' AND WITHOUT ANY EXPRESS OR
 IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE IMPLIED
 WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
-->
]>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>The History of BZFlag</title>
    <subtitle>as told by <firstname>Chris</firstname> <surname>Schoeneman</surname></subtitle>
    <pubdate>2003-12-04</pubdate>

    <author>
      <firstname>Chris</firstname>
      <surname>Schoeneman</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>A brief history of BZFlag told by the original author
      himself.</para>
    </abstract>

  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="history">

    <sect1>

      <title>The History of BZFlag</title>

      <para>BZFlag began back in 1992 while I was a Masters student at
      the Cornell Program of Computer Graphics. I was an intern at SGI
      for the summers of '90 and '91, working on a prototype Indigo
      during the second summer which was a blast. So by 1992, IRIS GL
      was an old friend.</para>

      <para>At the Cornell PCG, essentially the only computers
      available were HP 700 series workstations. While CRX-24Z
      graphics wasn't too bad (around XS24-Z performance), HP's
      graphics library, Starbase, wasn't quite as easy to use as IRIS
      GL. In the words of fellow student Rick Pasetto, "Starbase sucks
      rocks." As a result, very few students wrote interactive
      graphics tools to assist their research. If you wanted to make
      an image you usually had to at least ray trace it.</para>

      <para>So Rick and I wrote an IRIS GL-like layer on top of
      Starbase which we called WM (it was originally for window
      management). To encourage the other students to use it I wrote a
      number of small demo programs, small being the key word
      here. The fact that you could open a window and render to it
      with only a dozen lines of code ensured WM's success. I think it
      was finally retired by 1999, replaced by OpenGL.</para>

      <para>I began to write BZFlag as a simple demo but soon
      abandoned it after producing a program that was supposed to let
      you drive around a virtual world but instead had a bizarre
      warping effect because I goofed up the order of my
      transformations. I had by then also realized how much more work
      was involved and had other stuff to do.</para>

      <para>So there it sat, unused, for a few months until another
      student browsing the WM demo directory found it and said it
      looked cool and that I should finish it. So in a week long
      marathon of programming BZFlag took shape. The earliest complete
      version had two notable bugs. The first was that each player had
      his very own random world; it was soon discovered that hiding
      behind a pyramid didn't work because the pyramid wasn't even
      there in the other player's world. Once that was fixed, the
      second bug became clear: it was impossible to play. I had tried
      to base the BZFlag world on the real world, so the playing field
      was 10km on a side and shots moved at around Mach 1. It took
      forever to get from one end of the board to the other and you
      couldn't even see a shot before it hit you.  So we scrapped some
      realism in favor of playability. After a few more tweaks, we had
      a pretty fun game.</para>

      <para>At this point the game resembled bz by Chris Fouts. This
      is no surprise because both games are based on the old Atari
      arcade game BattleZone. In fact, BZFlag was called bz back then
      because no one in the PCG knew of the existence of Chris Fouts'
      bz. Yes, that's right, BZFlag was written with no knowledge of
      bz. The two games share no code and were designed and written
      independently. They owe their similarities to their BattleZone
      heritage.</para>

      <para>It didn't take too long to get bored with the basic
      shoot-'em-up game. We quickly came up with the capture-the-flag
      mode and designed the new world it's played in. This kept our
      interest for quite a while (it's still my favorite
      mode). Strategy now played a role. You still needed good tactics
      to keep yourself alive, but you had to have a team strategy to
      excel.</para>

      <para>After one of the students hacked the code to make his tank
      super-powerful (blatantly so; he wasn't trying to fool us) we
      invented superflags. The first four super flags were: high
      speed, quick turn, rapid fire, and oscillation
      overthruster. Originally, there was one of each flag and each
      had an identifying mark so you knew what it was before you
      grabbed it. When more superflag ideas came up (including the
      concept of bad flags) we dropped the marks and made the flags
      appear randomly.  This was around May 1993 and the game has
      remained substantially the same ever since. I rewrote the game
      in C++ (from C) for SGI's third IndiZone contest. BZFlag won in
      the Reality Engine category, earning me a nice little home
      computer (a Indigo2 200MHz R4400, with a 20" monitor, 64MB, a
      CD-ROM, DAT, 2GB disk, and High Impact graphics with 4
      TRAMs).</para>

      <note>crs claims the first release was the first week of 1993 so
      we are over 10 years old now.</note>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>

      <title>Previous versions of the BZFlag website</title>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><ulink url="http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://reality.sgi.com/crs/bzflag.html">http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://reality.sgi.com/crs/bzflag.html</ulink></listitem>

        <listitem><ulink url="http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://bzflag.linuxgames.com/">http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://bzflag.linuxgames.com/</ulink></listitem>

        <listitem><ulink url="http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://bzflag.sourceforge.net/">http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://bzflag.sourceforge.net/</ulink></listitem>

        <listitem><ulink url="http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://BZFlag.org/">http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://BZFlag.org/</ulink></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </sect1>

  </chapter>

</book>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- mode: SGML -->
<!-- tab-width: 8 -->
<!-- c-basic-offset: 2 -->
<!-- indent-tabs-mode: t -->
<!-- End: -->
<!--
 ex: shiftwidth=2 tabstop=8
-->
