<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!--
 Copyright (c) 1993 - 2007 Tim Riker

 This package is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 it under the terms of the license found in the file named COPYING
 that should have accompanied this file.

 THIS PACKAGE IS PROVIDED ``AS IS'' AND WITHOUT ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
 WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
 MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
-->
]>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Karma</title>
    <pubdate>2003-12-04</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
    </copyright>

  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="karma">

    <screen>

= KarmaSystem =

There has been a lot of talk about a KarmaSystem for ["BZFlag"]. This
page is to collect ideas about it. This document outline some ideas of
the upcoming player database and karma system. This is work in
progress.

= Current Plans =

TimRiker is asking for help in creating and moving to a new system
with DbServers that implement the KarmaSystem.

The First 3 Sections only give a short description of the basic ideas.
Section 4 contains some ideas on how to implement them. This is where
you are invited to bring in your ideas.

= Links =

 * http://Advogato.org/ - free software group trust metrics
 * http://keyserver.kjsl.com/~jharris/ka/current/ - GPG trust matrix analysis
 * http://ggz.sourceforge.net/ - possible platform, not planned at present

= Objectives =

There are two main objectives:
 * prevent misuse of callsigns
 * solve cheating issues on the social level

= Player Database =

The player database keeps entries for registered players. Each entry
must at least contain the player's callsign, email address and some
data to allow for authentication. This data must be accessible by
public bzfs servers so that these can screen joining players. Any
changes require private key signed updates.

= Karma System =

With the karma system, a rating - the so-called karma - is assigned to
each registered player in the database. This value should represent
the player's reputation within the community, i.e. well-known and nice
players should have a high karma value whereas known cheaters will
hopefully get a low value.

BZFlag servers can access this information and for example prevent
people with too bad karma from joining the server. Players must have
some means to rate other players, thus modifying their karma. It is
important that the karma system is balanced and robust against abuse.

= Implementation =

== player database / authentication ==

 * The player database will be located in the central list server because this
 is a central service already.

 * Authentication can be done by using a simple public key scheme. A
 player must be able to create an identity, i.e. a unique callsign and
 a keypair. The local and public key will be stored in the client
 config locally. The public key will be uploaded to the player
 database when registering. When a player needs to prove his identity,
 his client will sign a challenge with his private key. The party
 doing the authentication challenge can then verify this by using the
 player's public key from the database.

 * Should a client be able to manage several identities from which a
 player can choose?

 * It could be possible to play without registering as a guest on open
 servers. This might just be a transparent temporary registration if
 that is easier to deal with.

 * Security issues: Should the private key be encrypted with a
 passphrase? Should the list server and each BZFlag server also have
 to authenticate themselves? I guess we do not have too high security
 standards here, so for example we do not need to encrypt all
 communication to prevent session hijacking and other attacks.

 * Is it a good idea to allow a registered player to authenticate
 himself and still play with a different callsign if he wants to play
 anonymously? E.g., let's say a well-reputed player registered as
 'GrimReaper', authenticates himself when joining a server who
 requires a high karma value, but is visible to the other players as
 'Bozo'. - they still would not be allowed to use another registered
 nickname as their callsign.

 * The data that is stored for each player in the database could include:
  * callsign (required)
  * public key (required)
  * email address (required)
  * full name
  * statistics: time of registration (age), last time of play, total playing time, time spent on different servers, with different settings etc.
  * karma data

 Which of these should be mandatory?

 * In addition to the stats data mentioned above we could also try to
 implement an automatic rating of the player's strength, similar to
 the Elo rating for chess players, maybe differentiating for different
 styles, server settings.

== Registration process ==

Registration should be easy and can either be done with the BZFlag
client or an extra executable for managing identities. The client will
connect to the list server and send the data for the new player. The
list server will acknowledge this if there is no callsign clash.

For changing the player data (like email address) later on, the client
first needs to successfully authenticate itself by using the usual
challenge/response procedure.

== karma system ==

 * A new player starts with a neutral karma value, I guess 0 is a
 natural starting point :-). Karma might be an integer of a floating
 point value.

 * Each BZFlag server can be configured to require a minimum karma
 value for each player. When a player does not meet this criterion, he
 will be rejected. Hopefully, this reduced cheating on these 'high
 quality' servers. Of course there should also be some servers which
 are open to everyone, otherwise new players could never play and
 increase their karma. Server admins should balance reasons for
 specifying a low karma threshold, and thus allowing everyone to play
 on their server or requiring very high karma and possible improve the
 quality of people playing, but at the cost of ruling out many players
 and possibly having a very empty server.

 * the server could also be configured with a minimum admin
 karma. Players that meet the criteria would be able to change server
 options, kick players etc. We may want multiple levels of admin
 access.

 * There must be a convenient way for a player to rate another
 player. I guess it's best to be able to do this in-game. Should
 rating just be done by using +/- resp. up/down? Or by giving a value
 from -5 to 5? For this to be easy, the player to be rated must be
 selected in some way. How? A player should be able to see the rank he
 has given other players easily. Perhaps even on the scoreboard.

 * When doing ratings in-game, either the client or the server must
 send messages to the list server. It's probably best if the client
 sends a signed update to the server and the server forwards it (with
 game updates as well) to the list server and then updates the rated
 player info if the list server verifies the signed update packet. The
 signature is required so that the list server can verify the source
 of the ranking. Servers might otherwise fake ratings.

 * Should karma value and/or individual ratings be publicly visible /
 visible to the player himself? Tim thinks so. Players should be able
 to see who has ranked them, but not what rank they have been
 given. They should be able to see all the players they have ranked at
 what rank they have given them. They should also be able to see any
 player's rank including their own.

 * The karma value of a player must be calculated as a function of all
 individual ratings from other players. This must be done in a 'fair'
 way that is robust against misuse. A possible misuse would be a
 player A registering a lot of identities and giving a low rating to
 player B with all of his identities. So, ratings must be weighted by
 karma and player age. This must be designed very carefully, so I
 suggest stealing this from somewhere. It will be necessary to store
 the resulting karma value for each player as well as every rating
 given.

 * Do we want or need some privileged players whose ratings have more
 weight? This might be needed to get the system started.

= Basic rules for karma adjustment =

 * A user can only have one karma value per other player. This can be changed at any point
 * Impact is determined by these factors:
 * Current rating
 * Assignment tendency (neutral = more impact, all good or all bad = less impact) [keep in mind that some users will ONLY rate players whom they like]
 * Player age - long-time players will have more influence
 * Playing time - people who spend their lives in BZFlag should have more power

= Possible implementation =

This is proton's idea:

Store the entire karma network as a weighted directed graph. Weights
along the edges should go from -5 to 5 or some other range specifying
the karma adjustment from one player to another. Each node would also
have a weight, calculated from the other factors listed above (age,
time, etc). When a karma adjustment is made, a walk of the graph is
done, computing everbody's new karma (if someone near the root gets
modded up, it could have repercussions through the entire tree,
strengthening the adjustments they themselves have made). Nodes
furthest from the root (note: the 'root' would be someone completely
trusted, like TimRiker) have the lowest karma.

With this scheme, bad accounts could be deleted by the same type of
algorithm as used for Advogato's trust metric, setting up a supersink
and cutting away all bad nodes, thus preventing abuse.

= Other database items =

The KarmaSystem would use a central server (or servers) to store the
data. TimRiker imagines that this system would include other useful
bits like player ladder ranks, league membership, league ranks, map
ranks, etc. It may contain gpg signatures, ssh public keys, or perhaps
the karma server is a certificate authority for ssl keys and server
keys and player keys are authenticated there. The player keys could
actually be presented to the users's browser and use that information
to log in to the karma website.

= Karma Web Site =

The website would show overall ranks for players on the trust scale
and probably also ladder ranks, live servers, server stats, player
stats, etc. A player would need to authenticate to edit settings. This
page would show everyone this player has ranked and the rank they
currently have. These would be highlighted to show if those players
have ranked this player too. There would be a separate list of people
that have ranked this player colored to show if this player has also
ranked them. The actual ranks are not shown to encourage fair ranking.

Well, probably a whole bunch of stuff is still missing. Feel free to
add anything.

    </screen>

  </chapter>

</book>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- mode: SGML -->
<!-- tab-width: 8 -->
<!-- c-basic-offset: 2 -->
<!-- indent-tabs-mode: t -->
<!-- End: -->
<!--
 ex: shiftwidth=2 tabstop=8
-->
